<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1">
  <title id="dr20941">RETRIEVE</title>
  <body>
    <p id="sql_command_desc">Retrieves rows from a query using a parallel retrieve cursor.</p>
    <section id="section2">
      <title>Synopsis</title>
      <codeblock id="sql_command_synopsis">RETRIEVE { &lt;count> | ALL } FROM ENDPOINT &lt;endpoint_name></codeblock>
    </section>
    <section id="section3">
      <title>Description</title>
      <p><codeph>RETRIEVE</codeph> retrieves rows using a previously-created parallel
        retrieve cursor. You retrieve the rows in individual retrieve sessions, separate direct
        connections to individual segment endpoints that will serve the results for each individual segment.
         When you initiate a retrieve session, you must specify
           <xref href="../config_params/guc-list.html#gp_retrieve_conn"
             format="html" scope="peer">gp_retrieve_conn=true</xref>
         on the connection request. Because a retrieve session is independent of the
         parallel retrieve cursors or their corresponding endpoints, you can
         <codeph>RETRIEVE</codeph> from multiple endpoints in the same retrieve session.</p>
      <p>A parallel retrieve cursor has an associated position, which is used by
        <codeph>RETRIEVE</codeph>. The cursor position can be before the first row of the
        query result, on any particular row of the result, or after the last row of the
        result.</p>
      <p>When it is created, a parallel retrieve cursor is positioned before the
        first row. After retrieving some rows, the cursor is positioned on the row most
        recently retrieved.</p>
      <p>If <codeph>RETRIEVE</codeph> runs off the end of the available rows then
        the cursor is left positioned after the last row.</p>
      <p><codeph>RETRIEVE ALL</codeph> always leaves the parallel retrieve cursor positioned
        after the last row.</p>
      <note>Greenplum Database does not support scrollable cursors; you can only move a
        cursor forward in position using the <codeph>RETRIEVE</codeph> command.</note>
      <sectiondiv id="section4">
        <b>Outputs</b>
        <p>On successful completion, a <codeph>RETRIEVE</codeph> command returns the fetched
          rows (possibly empty) and a count of the number of rows fetched (possibly
          zero).</p>
      </sectiondiv>
    </section>
    <section id="section5">
      <title>Parameters</title>
        <parml>
          <plentry>
            <pt><varname>count</varname></pt>
            <pd>Retrieve the next <varname>count</varname> number of rows.
              <varname>count</varname> must be a positive number.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>ALL</pt>
            <pd>Retrieve all remaining rows.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt><varname>endpoint_name</varname></pt>
            <pd>The name of the endpoint from which to retrieve the rows.</pd>
          </plentry>
        </parml>
    </section>
    <section id="section6">
      <title>Notes</title>
      <p>Use <codeph>DECLARE ... PARALLEL RETRIEVE CURSOR</codeph> to define a parallel
        retrieve cursor.</p>
      <p>Parallel retrieve cursors do not support <codeph>FETCH</codeph> or
        <codeph>MOVE</codeph> operations.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="section7">
      <title>Examples</title>
      <p>-- Start the transaction:</p>
      <codeblock>BEGIN;</codeblock>
      <p>-- Create a parallel retrieve cursor:</p>
      <codeblock>DECLARE mycursor PARALLEL RETRIEVE CURSOR FOR SELECT * FROM films;</codeblock>
      <p>-- List the cursor endpoints:</p>
      <codeblock>SELECT * FROM gp_endpoints WHERE cursorname='mycursor';</codeblock>
      <p>-- Note the hostname, port, auth_token, and name associated with each endpoint.</p>
      <p>-- In another terminal window, initiate a retrieve session using a hostname, port, and auth_token returned from the previous query. For example:</p>
      <codeblock>PGPASSWORD=d3825fc07e56bee5fcd2b1d0b600c85e PGOPTIONS='-c gp_retrieve_conn=true' psql -d testdb -h sdw3 -p 6001;</codeblock>
      <p>-- Fetch all rows from an endpoint (for example, the endpoint named <codeph>prc10000001100000005</codeph>):</p>
      <codeblock>RETRIEVE ALL FROM ENDPOINT prc10000001100000005;</codeblock>
      <p>-- Exit the retrieve session</p>
      <p>-- Back in the original session, close the cursor and end the transaction:</p>
      <codeblock>CLOSE mycursor;
COMMIT;</codeblock>
    </section>
    <section id="section8">
      <title>Compatibility</title>
      <p><codeph>RETRIEVE</codeph> is a Greenplum Database extension. The SQL standard makes
        no provisions for parallel retrieve cursors.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="section9">
      <title>See Also</title>
        <p><xref href="DECLARE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/>,
          <xref href="CLOSE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>

